PT	AU	BE	TI	X1	Y1	Z1	SO	LA	DT	DE	X5	Y5	Z5	AB	X4	Y4	Z4	C1	EM	RI	OI	CR	NR	TC	Z9	U1	U2	PU	PI	PA	SN	PD	PY	VL	IS	BP	EP	DI	EC	C2	SC	UT	OA	HC	HP	DA
J	Botta, Robson Antonio; Silva, Fernando Felisberto da; Pazini, Juliano de Bastos; Martins, José Francisco da Silva; Rubenich, Rodrigo		Abundância sazonal de percevejo-do-colmo do arroz	Seasonal abundance of rice stem bug			Pesquisa Agropecuária Tropical		research-article					The rice stem bug (Tibraca limbativentris) population has increased over the last years making it one of the main pests in irrigated rice crops in Planalto da Campanha, Rio Grande do Sul State, Brazil. Favorable factors throughout the year provide conditions for its infestation in crops and subsequent hibernation. This study aimed to determine the variation of rice stem bug population in commercial irrigated rice crop and hibernation sites. Therefore, a population survey of nymphs and adults was carried out. It was concluded that the photoperiod and temperature were the factors that most affected the insect population, leading to a hibernation period of 10 months. Management operations also affected the population reduction.		A população de percevejo-do-colmo (Tibraca limbativentris) vem elevando-se, nos últimos anos, posicionando-o como uma das principais pragas da cultura do arroz irrigado, na região do Planalto da Campanha do Rio Grande do Sul. Fatores favoráveis ao longo do ano propiciam condições para sua infestação nas lavouras e posterior hibernação. O presente estudo objetivou verificar a variação populacional do percevejo do-colmo, em condições de lavoura comercial de arroz irrigado e sítios de hibernação. Para tanto, realizou-se levantamento populacional de ninfas e adultos. Verificou-se que o fotoperíodo e a temperatura foram os fatores que mais afetaram a população do inseto, levando a um período de hibernação de 10 meses. As operações de manejo também influenciaram na redução da população.					Felisberto da Silva, Fernando/0000-0003-1229-896X										1983-4063	12	2014	44	4	417	423	10.1590/S1983-40632014000400014				SCIELO:S1983-40632014000400014	gold				
J	Specht, A; Iltchenco, J; Fronza, E; Roque-Specht, VF; Luz, PC; Montezzano, DG		Biological aspects of Tiracola grandirena (Herrich-Schäffer, 1868) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae): a polyphagous armyworm	Aspectos biológicos de Tiracola grandirena (Herrich-Schäffer, 1868) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae): uma lagarta polífaga			Brazilian Journal of Biology		research-article					We studied the biology of Tiracola grandirena (Herrich-Schäffer, 1868) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae: Hadeninae) at 25 ± 1 °C, 70 ± 10% RH and 14 hours of photo phase. Three experiments, using 150 larvae each, were conducted for the larval stage. In the first, used to assess the duration and survival of all stages, insects were reared individually and fed an artificial diet (Grenee). In the second, individuals were also reared separately, but were fed leaves of 10 plants from different families. In the third, the larvae were not individualised, the food plants were rotated such as to provide three plant species every 48 hours. In the first experiment, the viability of the eggs, larvae, pupae and prepupae was 91.9, 94.7, 32.49 and 43.5%, respectively. The average duration of the egg, larvae, prepupae, pupae and adult were 6.0, 25.3, 25.7, 21.4 and 12.7 days, respectively. The prolonged prepupal period indicates that T. grandirena can develop larval (prepupal) diapause. The results of the experiments with different host plants showed that T. grandirena is polyphagous at species, population and individual level.		Estudou-se a biologia de Tiracola grandirena (Herrich-Schäffer, 1868) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae: Hadeninae) em condições controladas de 25 ± 1 °C, 70 ± 10% UR e fotofase de 14 horas. Na fase larval foram estabelecidos três experimentos empregando 150 larvas cada. No primeiro, os insetos foram criados individualmente, com dieta artificial de Grenee, cujos dados foram utilizados para avaliar a duração e a sobrevivência das larvas, pupas e adultos. No segundo, as larvas foram criadas individualmente, alimentadas com folhas de 10 plantas de famílias diferentes avaliando-se a sobrevivência e duração larval (fase ativa). No terceiro, as larvas foram mantidas em um mesmo recipiente, variando-se a alimentação vegetal, três espécies a cada 48 horas, avaliando-se apenas a sobrevivência larval. No primeiro experimento a viabilidade de ovo, larva, pré-pupa e pupa foi de 91,93; 94,67; 32,39 e 43,48%, respectivamente. A duração média de ovo, larva, pré-pupa, pupa e adulto foi de 6,00; 25,26; 25,76; 21,35 e 12,67 dias, respectivamente. O prolongado período de pré-pupa indicou que, nas condições em que foi criada T. grandirena pode desenvolver diapausa larval (pré-pupal). Os resultados dos experimentos com diferentes plantas hospedeiras demonstraram que T. grandirena é polífaga ao nível específico, populacional e individual.				Specht, Alexandre/P-8435-2019; Roque-Specht, Vânia/J-1306-2014; Fronza, Edegar/J-1247-2014; Specht, Alexandre/G-6007-2012	Specht, Alexandre/0000-0002-8921-0340; Fronza, Edegar/0000-0003-0463-9728; Specht, Alexandre/0000-0002-8921-0340										1678-4375	02	2014	74	1	205	211	10.1590/1519-6984.12212				SCIELO:S1519-69842014000100025	gold				
J	Specht, Alexandre; Angulo, Andrés O.; Olivares, Tania S.; Fronza, Edegar; Roque-Specht, Vânia F.; Valduga, Eduardo; Albrecht, Francine; Poletto, Graziela; Barros, Neiva M.		Life cycle of Agrotis malefida (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae): a diapausing cutworm				Zoologia (Curitiba)		research-article					This study describes the life cycle of Agrotis malefida Guenée, 1852 (Noctuidae: Noctuinae) under laboratory conditions. The insects were reared in a controlled environment (25 ± 1ºC, 70 ± 10% RH and 14 hours photo phase) and observed daily. The larvae were fed Greene's artificial diet and adults were offered a 10% sucrose solution. The viability and duration of immature stages were assessed. The experiment initiated with 2,410 eggs. Larvae were isolated shortly after hatching. Longevity, pre-, post- and oviposition, fecundity and fertility of 13 adult couples were also evaluated. The viability of eggs, larvae, pupae and pre-pupae was 96.72, 91.25, 78.37 and 95.26%, respectively. The average duration of egg, larva, pre-pupa, pupa and adult was 7.93, 54.26, 61.61, 37.43 and 12.85 days, respectively. The immature stage of A. malefida lasted an average of 161.29 days, ranging from 102 to 227 days. The life cycle of A. malefida is much longer than that of congeners. The mean fecundity was 1,696.77 eggs and fertility 1,641.15 larvae per female. Under the conditions in which the study was conducted, the biotic potential of A. malefida was of 606,666.59 individuals/female/year. The results also indicated that this species goes through larval (pre-pupae) and pupal diapause.						Specht, Alexandre/G-6007-2012; Specht, Alexandre/P-8435-2019; Roque-Specht, Vânia/J-1306-2014; Fronza, Edegar/J-1247-2014	Specht, Alexandre/0000-0002-8921-0340; Specht, Alexandre/0000-0002-8921-0340; Fronza, Edegar/0000-0003-0463-9728										1984-4689	08	2013	30	4	371	378	10.1590/S1984-46702013000400002				SCIELO:S1984-46702013000400002	gold				
J	Silveira, Luís Cláudio Paterno; Bueno, Vanda Helena Paes		Orius insidiosus (Say, 1832) (Heteroptera, Anthocoridae): sensibilidade ao fotoperíodo e diapausa reprodutiva?	Orius insidiosus (Say, 1832) (Heteroptera, Anthocoridae): sensitivity to diapause-inducting photoperiods?			Revista Brasileira de Entomologia		case-report					The minute pirate bugs, Orius spp., are known as predators on several pests as thrips, aphids, spider mites and whiteflies. Orius insidiosus is an important thrips predator, commercially used around the world. However, one of the main problems on biological control of thrips in temperate regions is the occurrence of reproductive diapause in Orius species. This characteristic promotes the interruption of biological control strategies when predators are exposed to short photoperiods. This research had as objective to evaluate the influence of different photoperiod conditions on eggs/nymphs and adults of O. insidiosus in laboratory. The trials were carried out through the combination of eggs/nymphs and adults reared under the photoperiods 10L:14D; 11L:13D; 12L:12D and 13L:11D, at 25±2ºC and 70±10% RH. The predators were maintained during their pre-imaginal development time under one of the photoperiods and, after being emerged as adults transferred to another photoperiod regime. The predator had a tendency to present longer development time under photoperiod 13L:11D. There was no influence of the different photoperiods conditions on the reproduction of O. insidiosus. The females laid eggs normally during all their lifetime. O. insidiosus is not sensitive to photoperiod evaluated and do not enter in reproductive diapause.																	1806-9665	12	2003	47	4	631	635	10.1590/S0085-56262003000400016				SCIELO:S0085-56262003000400016	gold				
